Inventory of the Great Hollow Wilderness School/WOW Collection, 1985 - 1999
Great Hollow Wilderness School/WOW Collection, 1985 - 1999
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Great Hollow Wilderness School (New Fairfield, Conn.)
1995-1
1.5
3
In 1969, Peter Budryk opened the Great Hollow Wilderness School (GHWS) to provide disadvantaged children and teenagers with a wilderness experience. In 1985, the GHWS offered a Wesleyan Orientation in the Wilderness (WOW) program for incoming freshmen at Wesleyan University.
The Great Hollow Wilderness School/WOW Collection includes files with information about both programs, and objects given to participants, such as water bottles, t-shirts, and hats.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by Erhard Konerding in summer 1995.
Historical Note
In the late 1960s, a 1,440 acre wildlife preserve in New Fairfield was willed to Wesleyan University by Walter Gordon Merritt. The land was named Great Hollow and in 1969, Peter Budryk, with the moral support of Murray Durst, created the Great Hollow Wilderness School (GHWS), a sort of combination of Upward Bound and Outward Bound: a wilderness program for disadvantaged youth. After the first year of the program in 1970, Budryk developed a graduate course in the Wesleyan Master of Arts in Teaching program in outdoor education leadership; after a few years, the course was no longer needed as a group of capable GHWS staff were available. In 1973, Budryk was named executive director of the program and was given full responsibility for its development and operation. In 1982, the Wilderness Education Association invited and accredited GHWS to conduct the National Standard Program in Outdoor Leadership Certification.
In 1985, GHWS was given approval to run an optional freshman orientation trip. The first Wesleyan Orientation in the Wilderness (WOW) in 1985 was very successful and the program continued through the 1990s.
Collection Overview
The Great Hollow Wilderness School/WOW Collection includes files with information about both programs, and objects given to participants, such as water bottles, t-shirts, and hats.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Great Hollow Wilderness School (New Fairfield, Conn.); Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Budryk, Peter.; Wilderness areas--Connecticut.; T-shirts.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - A History of WOW artifacts (Box 1)
  - WOW red and white flip-top water bottle (Box 1)
  - WOW 6 (1990) clear water bottle with straw (Box 1)
  - WOW 7 (1991) clear water bottle with straw (Box 1)
  - WOW 8 (1992) clear water bottle with straw (Box 1)
  - WOW 9 (1993) plastic mug (Box 1)
  - WELcome (Wesleyan Experiential Learning) flip-top water bottle (Box 1)
  - Wesleyan University Northeast Fish Tech Kids Fishing Camp green hat (Box 2)
  - WOW 3 Great Hollow Wilderness School Wesleyan University black t-shirt (Box 2)
  - WOW 5 Staff white t-shirt (Box 2)
  - Great Hollow Wilderness School red t-shirt (Box 2)
  - WOW 4 hat (Box 2)
  - Great Hollow Wilderness School white t-shirt (with WOW cardinal logo on the back) (Box 2)
  - Great Hollow Wilderness School grey t-shirt with green writing (Box 2)
  - GHWS Historical Overview (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - GHWS Programs/Courses (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - GHWS Maps and Guides (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - GHWS Staff/Personnel (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - GHWS Advisory Committee 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - GHWS 1985 Student Evaluations (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - WOW 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - WOW Summer 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - WOW 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - WOW 1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - WOW EK draft article, citations to other articles (Box 3, Folder 11)